<anewt:chapter
	xmlns:anewt="http://anewt.net/ns/2008/04/documentation"
	id="introduction"
	>

	<anewt:title>Introduction</anewt:title>

	<anewt:section id="what-is-anewt">
		
		<anewt:title>What is Anewt?</anewt:title>

		<p>The <strong>Almost No Effort Web Toolkit</strong> is a collection
			of PHP libraries designed to aid rapid web development.</p>

		<p>Anewt is not a web framework, although nothing prevents you to
			build one using it. Anewt provides you with all the tools without
			forcing you to organize your project in a specific way. That means
			you can use your own preferred directory layout, filenames, etc.
			This makes Anewt both suited for new projects and for integration
			in existing projects.</p>

		<p>The modules in Anewt help you quickly create fully
			standards-compliant dynamic web sites and web applications. It
			consists of a number of modules which help you work with strict
			XHTML pages, text formatting, database abstraction and validation,
			form creation and handling and other web-related things like
			session control and syndication. Anewt is entirely written in PHP
			and it is assumed you use a reasonably recent version.</p>

	</anewt:section>

	<anewt:section id="structure">
		
		<anewt:title>Structure of this manual</anewt:title>

		<p>The overview chapter gives a general introduction to Anewt. The
			basic concepts and the structure of the Anewt package will be
			explained. This chapter is recommended for all readers.</p>

		<p>The following chapters gives you some advice on how to use Anewt.
			You are in no way required to follow these guidelines and
			conventions, but the project structure outlined in these chapters
			may be of great help to new users.</p>

		<p>The remaining chapters (quite a few) each deal with an Anewt
			module. The <anewt:moduleref>core</anewt:moduleref> module is used
			by almost all other modules, so you are highly recommended to read
			the chapter about it.</p>

		<p>You don't need to read all those chapters to start using Anewt,
			but since some modules depend on other modules, you will need at
			least some basic knowledge of the module that is built upon.</p>

	</anewt:section>

	<anewt:section id="feedback-support-contributions">
		
		<anewt:title>Feedback, support and contributions</anewt:title>

		<p><strong>Let us know what you think!</strong> We are interested in
			all comments, complaints and, of course, compliments from our
			users. User feedback helps us improve Anewt.</p>

		<p><strong>Bugs, issues and feature requests</strong> can be
			reported in our <a
				href="https://launchpad.net/products/anewt/+bugs">bug tracking
				system</a>. Describe your problem clearly and include a small
			test case if possible.</p>
			
		<p>You can also <strong>join our IRC channel</strong>
			<code>#anewt</code> on OFTC (irc.oftc.net) to have a chat with
			developers and other users. Just ask your question and wait
			patiently. We're not always available for chatting right away.</p>
	
		<p><strong>Become a contributor!</strong> If you're implementing a
			cool new feature or fixing an issue, please file a bug for it, so
			that we we can track development and no work is duplicated.
			Patches to Anewt can be submitted as attachments to bug reports.
			If you choose to publish your changes as a public accessible
			branch, please comment on the bug telling where to find your
			branch.</p>
			
		<p>Before publishing your code, make sure you've read the file
			<anewt:fileref>HACKING</anewt:fileref> in the top level Anewt
			directory. It contains information about our code guidelines and
			conventions. The Anewt source code is intended to be easily
			understandable, so all functions and methods must be documented
			(using Doxygen syntax), code must be well formatted and code
			comments should be written for all non-obvious code
			constructs.</p>

	</anewt:section>

</anewt:chapter>

<!-- vim: set tw=72 : -->
