<anewt:module
	xmlns:anewt="http://anewt.net/ns/2008/04/documentation"
	id="core"
	>

	<anewt:title>Core module</anewt:title>

	<anewt:subtitle>Core functions and classes</anewt:subtitle>

	<anewt:classes>
		<anewt:class>AnewtException</anewt:class>
		<anewt:class>AnewtRequest</anewt:class>
		<anewt:class>AnewtURL</anewt:class>
		<anewt:class>AnewtContainer</anewt:class>
	</anewt:classes>


	<p>The core module contains all basic routines offered by Anewt.
		This module is loaded by default upon when Anewt is initialized.
		Most functions are related to strings and arrays. The widely used
		<anewt:classref>AnewtContainer</anewt:classref> object is in the
		core module as well. Additionally, some other useful functions are
		provided. This chapter only covers the basic functionality offered
		by the core module; see the API documentation and the source code
		(quite readable and pretty well documented, really) for a full
		reference.</p>

	<anewt:section>

		<anewt:title>String functions</anewt:title>

		<p>PHP itself offers a lot of string utility functions, but some
			<strong>commonly used string logic routines</strong> are not
			implemented as simple, separarate functions. Often, this leads to
			duplication of (often simple but boring) micro-routines. A good
			example of this is the
			<anewt:functionref>str_contains()</anewt:functionref>
			function that checks whether a string contains a given substring.
			Of course you could also have used
			<anewt:functionname>strpos()</anewt:functionname>
			directly, but since this function can return both integers and
			boolean <code>false</code>, some care has to be taken every
			time you need this functionality. That's why Anewt provides you
			with a <anewt:functionref>str_contains()</anewt:functionref> function that hides
			these tiny details from view, so that you can concentrate on the
			meaning of your own code, instead of fiddling with PHP internals.
			A second example of this is
			<anewt:functionref>str_is_whitespace()</anewt:functionref>.
			Of course you could've used <code>(strlen(trim($str)) == 0)</code>,
			but once again: using meaningful functions keeps your code
			maintainable.</p>

		<p>Several functions are provided to deal with <strong>string
				prefixes and suffixes</strong>. The names speak for
			themselves: <anewt:functionref>str_has_prefix()</anewt:functionref>,
			<anewt:functionref>str_has_whitespace_prefix()</anewt:functionref>,
			<anewt:functionref>str_has_suffix()</anewt:functionref>,
			<anewt:functionref>str_has_whitespace_suffix()</anewt:functionref>,
			<anewt:functionref>str_strip_suffix()</anewt:functionref>, and
			<anewt:functionref>str_strip_prefix()</anewt:functionref>. See the API reference for
			more information.</p>

		<p>A useful <strong>string truncation</strong> routine,
			<anewt:functionref>str_truncate()</anewt:functionref>, is provided to cut off
			strings at a given length. This is very useful if you want to
			display overview pages with only a certain number of characters
			instead of the whole bunch of text.</p>
		
		<p>Some other functions let you deal with arrays of strings
			easily:
			<anewt:functionref>str_first_non_white()</anewt:functionref> and
			<anewt:functionref>str_all_non_white()</anewt:functionref>. Once again, the names
			speak for themselves.</p>

	</anewt:section>


	<anewt:section>

		<anewt:title>Array functions</anewt:title>

		<p>The array functions offered by Anewt are written in the same
			spirit as the string functions outlined in the previous section.
			PHP itself has a lot of array related functions. Anewt tries to
			fill in the missing pieces to make arrays a pleasure to deal
			with.</p>

		<p>PHP makes no difference between lists and hashes. Lists are
			simply lists of values (called numerical arrays in PHP), while
			hashes (also known as dictionaries or hash tables, called
			associative arrays in PHP) contain key/value pairs. Lists in PHP
			are implemented as hashes with numerical keys, while hashes use
			string keys. The values can be of any type. The built-in
			<anewt:functionname>is_array()</anewt:functionname> cannot be used to differentiate
			between these types. Anewt offers
			<anewt:functionref>is_numeric_array()</anewt:functionref> and
			<anewt:functionref>is_assoc_array()</anewt:functionref> functions to do this for
			you.</p>

		<anewt:warning>
			
			<p>PHP allows you to mix lists and hashes by using both
				integer and string keys in the same array. You are strongly
				discouraged to do this. It makes your code a
				mess!</p>
		
		</anewt:warning>

		<p>The function
			<anewt:functionref>array_get_default()</anewt:functionref> is
			useful to get a value from an array, providing a default value if
			the given key was not present in the array. Use this function to
			to get values from arrays with optional configuration data (e.g.
			config files). This saves you from a lot of checking code, as the
			example below shows: </p>

		<anewt:example src="core-array-get-default">
			<anewt:title>Retrieving data (providing default values) from arrays</anewt:title>
		</anewt:example>

		<p>The function
			<anewt:functionref>array_set_default()</anewt:functionref> is
			similar to
			<anewt:functionref>array_get_default()</anewt:functionref>, setting
			values in arrays if no value was set before:</p>

		<anewt:example src="core-array-set-default">
			<anewt:title>Setting default values in arrays</anewt:title>
		</anewt:example>

		<p>Anewt also provides a method to nicely format an array as a
			string: <anewt:functionref>array_format()</anewt:functionref>. Other routines allow
			you to retrieve certain data types from arrays:
			<anewt:functionref>array_get_int()</anewt:functionref> and
			<anewt:functionref>array_get_bool()</anewt:functionref>. Several other methods are
			provided, but not described in this section. See the API reference
			for more information.</p>

	</anewt:section>


	<anewt:section>

		<anewt:title>The <anewt:classref>AnewtContainer</anewt:classref> object</anewt:title>

		<p>The <anewt:classref>AnewtContainer</anewt:classref> class is one
		of the most useful classes provided by Anewt. It allows you to
		implement <strong>flexible and extensible data objects</strong>. The
		<anewt:classref>AnewtContainer</anewt:classref> class is intended to
		be extended by your own classes implementing your application logic.
		Your objects get the data handling functionality offered by the base
		<anewt:classref>AnewtContainer</anewt:classref> class for free.</p>

		<p>The <anewt:classref>AnewtContainer</anewt:classref> object is
		basically <strong>a wrapper around a hash</strong> (associative
		array) and can hold any data you provide, while adding the
		possibility to add very fine-grained control over which data can be
		kept in the object. This way you can easily start coding a fully
		functional class and add the necessary validation and output logic
		later. As long as you use your object in a standard way, calling
		code won't need any changes in case you decide to change the
		internal workings of your data object.</p>

		<p>The <anewt:classref>AnewtContainer</anewt:classref> object can be
		used to create clever (or nasty) hacks to manipulate data. Many
		other Anewt modules (such as the the page and forms modules) heavily
		use the <anewt:classref>AnewtContainer</anewt:classref>
		functionality.</p>

		<anewt:section>

			<anewt:title>Storing your data: getters and setters</anewt:title>

			<p>You can implement <strong>getter and setter methods</strong> to
			control which data can be retrieved from your object and which
			data can be stored in it. Note that you don't need to write getter
			and setter methods for each variable you want to store in the
			object: that's what the
			<anewt:classref>AnewtContainer</anewt:classref> class does for
			you. The
			<anewt:functionref>AnewtContainer::get()</anewt:functionref> and
			<anewt:functionref>AnewtContainer::set()</anewt:functionref>
			functions accept any key/value pair, but call into your own
			functions if you have implemented those. Getter functions should
			be named <code>get_foo</code>, where <code>foo</code> is the key
			provided to the
			<anewt:functionref>AnewtContainer::get()</anewt:functionref>
			function. The same idea goes for setter functions. Instead of
			calling the methods directly, you can also get and set the values
			by accessing those as instance properties. The example below shows
			some basic <anewt:classref>AnewtContainer</anewt:classref>
			usage:</p>

			<anewt:example src="core-container-getters-and-setters">
				<anewt:title>Basic container object usage with getter and setter methods</anewt:title>
			</anewt:example>

			<p>As you can see from the example, the
			<anewt:classref>AnewtContainer</anewt:classref> class allows you
			to retrieve dynamically generated data from your objects, e.g. by
			performing some calculations with other data in the object. The
			setter method makes sure no invalid data can be set on your
			object.</p>

			<p>For your convenience, a
			<anewt:functionref>AnewtContainer::seed()</anewt:functionref>
			function is provided to fill the
			<anewt:classref>AnewtContainer</anewt:classref> with data from an
			associative array. This is very useful to store the results of a
			database query: <code>$obj->seed($row_data)</code> is all you need
			to do.</p>

			<p>All magic methods offered by the
			<anewt:classref>AnewtContainer</anewt:classref> class have
			<strong>non-magic equivalents</strong> with the same name starting
			with an underscore, e.g.
			<anewt:functionref>AnewtContainer::_get()</anewt:functionref>,
			<anewt:functionref>AnewtContainer::set()</anewt:functionref>, and
			<anewt:functionref>AnewtContainer::_seed()</anewt:functionref>.
			These methods do not do any magic, but just store or retrieve data
			on the object without calling into getter and setter methods. This
			is considerably faster, but does not offer you as much
			flexibility.</p>

		</anewt:section>

		<anewt:section>

			<anewt:title>Simple caching</anewt:title>

			<p>If your getter methods do computationally expensive operations,
			like querying data from a database or doing some heavy
			calculations, each <code>$obj->get('foo')</code> call will cause a
			lot of overhead. In some cases it might be worth using a
			<strong>simple caching mechanism</strong>: the dynamically
			generated value is stored in the container and used on subsequent
			<code>$obj->get('foo')</code> calls. To use caching, you append an
			underscore to your getter method's name, so that it becomes
			<code>get_foo_()</code> instead of <code>get_foo()</code>. See
			also the example below:</p>

			<anewt:example src="core-container-caching">
				<anewt:title>Using simple caching in data objects</anewt:title>
			</anewt:example>

		</anewt:section>

	</anewt:section>

	<anewt:section>

		<anewt:title>The <anewt:classref>AnewtRequest</anewt:classref> class</anewt:title>

		<p>The <anewt:classref>AnewtRequest</anewt:classref> class provides
		several static methods to retrieve information about the current
		request. The relative and canonical (full) URL's for the current
		request can be retrieved using the
		<anewt:functionref>AnewtRequest::relative_url()</anewt:functionref>
		and
		<anewt:functionref>AnewtRequest::canonical_url()</anewt:functionref>
		methods. Furthermore, the request type can easily be determined by
		calling the
		<anewt:functionref>AnewtRequest::method()</anewt:functionref>,
		<anewt:functionref>AnewtRequest::is_get()</anewt:functionref> and
		<anewt:functionref>AnewtRequest::is_post()</anewt:functionref>
		methods. In addition, several methods to extract GET, POST or cookie
		data (with type-safety) are available. </p>

		<anewt:example src="core-request">
			<anewt:title>Retrieving request information</anewt:title>
		</anewt:example>

	</anewt:section>

	<anewt:section>

		<anewt:title>Miscellaneous</anewt:title>

		<p>TODO: redirect()</p>

		<p>TODO: constants</p>

		<p>TODO: mkenum</p>

	</anewt:section>

</anewt:module>

<!-- vim: set tw=72 : -->
